so again on the topic of non-conflict as
I found a quote from a jinn China
in what is called the core what manual
from what Panama chattel like the pumps
hmm core what is the monastery
etiquettes or the house rules of a
particular monastery says like Benaiah
is just the particular monasteries house
rules like for example your mother says you
like for example your mother says you
know don't walk inside the house issues
okay so you don't do and so this manual
is just tells you how to live within
that monastery so there's a number of
rules but again they don't come from the
buddha per se the book
also the the core what or vinaya is
usually used as a weapon hmm you know to
catch people out to prove that you're
right well I can only what you argue it's it's
well I can only what you argue it's it's
not used in the right way
hmm so this book begins with this urgent
charm quote innocent it's not right to
watch others with a fault-finding mind
this won't help you your whisper this
won't help your practice at all
if you feel annoyed observe that
annoyance in your heart if other people
sealer is not perfect well they do not
behave like good monks good people hmm
it is not your job to be judgemental you
won't become wise by watching and
blaming others the Vinaya is a tool to
assist you in developing Samadhi it is
not a weapon for finding fault or
judging who's good who's bad
no one can practice for you and you
can't practice for anyone else so be
mindful of your own behavior this is the
path of practice that's like the the
Buddhist type of a bible-bashing
yeah but no that's a person why like why
is the fault-finding
why is it bad you you [\h__\h] to anything
not specifically being out of something
but even what somebody says something
and they're wrong they might be
completely wrong in what they said but
why is you having a mind of looking for
faults why is that wrong for you there's
got nothing to do with you and they put
the parties wait are you yeah yeah
where's your fault well what is your
mind well no that's no okay but why is
looking for faults why is that a fault
if you're looking for fault you're
already at fault well you think you
aren't and folks that's kind of implicit
yeah yeah so you think you you're right
but why is it white why oh by another
reason why wouldn't why would it be also
fault
because it's like what we address
they're gonna be with you well yes
exactly yeah it comes from that framework a
yeah it comes from that framework a
predetermined framework of your mind
you're looking for fall to me you
already have a reason to look for faults
means doesn't matter what this person
says you're already looking for faults
you cannot look for faults on account of
understanding what they said you can
agree or disagree with what they've said
because you understood it but the mind
of looking for faults actually puts
whatever they said secondary and
prioritize that it's unlike irrational
approach approach of I'm looking for
faults now which means whatever it's
gonna be said it's gonna be seen against
the context for finding faults that's
what will I said that's one of the main
reasons the people be unable to develop
the right view even when they come
across the right teaching they have the
mind of fault finding and that's why
they will not understand that which they
would have otherwise understood and
become a sort of banner so that doesn't
mean you learn blanket accept everything
that said it doesn't mean you lose you
like a discriminative ability and and
discernment that means you don't give in
to the attitude of looking for faults
which is as I said independent of the
content that's being described or any
very solid before pretty much really
folks not going to point to them you
might have an inclination to look for
fault and simply ignoring that
inclination means that your mind state
in the same sense you might have an
inclination to resist or how you feel
resist towards the disagreeable and if
you ignore that means you're giving into
your world so you need to develop enough
self-awareness to be able to not
maintain the mind of looking for faults
even amidst things that you find
disagreeable but then if you does it
then if if that disagree ability is not
you looking for faults but it's rooted
in you understanding the meaning and
understanding the contradiction in the
meaning and understanding by that
meaning is wrong means that's absolutely
fine you can now dismiss that thing
because you understood it was wrong
so not just like and you will know that
like if you just hear something sent and
you say that from but you have no
argument as to why it's wrong and you
start to like scrape left and right
irrationally to justify why that's wrong
means you're only looking for faults and
you already chosen to not to accept that
even if you don't know really what it
means so you if you're accepting
something you want to know by you're
accepting it why it makes sense to you
why do you find this such a such
statement or teaching agreeable and say
if you're not accepting it you want to
know why you are not accepting it what
is wrong with it so if you say oh this
contradicts such-and-such you need to
know why and how to what extent not just
throw that oh this is just contradiction
by your notes no means of supporting it
or have extremely rational means of
supporting it it all points out that or
you already decided you don't wanna
accept this now you just need to justify
why that would be to your own they made
it basically because you might come
across things that are very accurate
very right and would have freed you from
suffering but because of your fault
finding mine is what I said you would
have not excellent there and gain the
understanding or did you dismissed it
beforehand and again if you're honest
with yourself you would ask I don't know
what the truth is but which is more
likely if I were to hear the truth which
is more likely to find in agreeable or
disagreeable just off the top of your
head what would be the first answer yes
it's not gonna be whatever it's of
course gonna be against my whole life
against the whole nature of being in
existence tamo goes against the stream against the
tamo goes against the stream against the
grain how's that gonna be felt if you
always want to be the grain so you
realize already you can even as a
petitioner who is not you know not a
monk not practicing fully community you
can actually still not forsake a good
line of reasoning
oh so it's more likely to be upsetting
so now you find things that have set you
but teachings that make you displeased
now understand what is that is it
because oh well because the way he
speaks well that's not an argument
that's not a valid argument
oh I'll dismiss what that person says
because of how they said it note that's
an excuse that's not an argument if you
want to dismiss what this person said or
if you want to accept what that person
said you need to understand why and not
just say but because it displeases me or
pleases me respectively that's a
rational basis for your understanding
does there is an understanding so if
some if you accept something you want to
know why why does this that make sense
to me if you don't want to accept that
you want to know why does this doesn't
make sense to me and then if you expand
the answer why it doesn't make sense to
you then question that answer see well
rather than answer make sense or you
just jumped on the answer because it
pleased you cuz it offer you like a
leeway to step back and ignore what you
heard and it was displeasing to you and
that's how only stop going against the
grain against the grain of accepting
things at the face value which is a
definition of human existence pretty
much
just to go back to nothing sharp quotes
if another person sealer is not perfect
what they do not behave like good monks
well your idea of a good monkeys it's
not your problem
yeah it's not your job to be judgemental
hmm it's not your problem
yeah and as I said previously that
doesn't mean you will be blind to the
behavior but if you dislike it you will
maybe start looking into why are you
disliking it as opposed to no we must
police that especially when there's
nothing wrong like because that's the
whole point of their court is it's not
the veneer so it's nothing immoral in
regard to not walking with shoes in your
house nothing immoral about it
that's why good Court is the color that
has a practical application basis bad
court is just whimsy called sort of
cards made by the people in the position
of power over junior ones but that's
beside the point the point is to
recognize whether you agree with the
comment or not and why is that why would
you mind that even if somebody done it
for wrong reasons simply to entertain
the sense of control over others they
create covered rules to see if everybody
will obey while your problem obeying
that is it because you're conceited is
why is it your problem so in the same
sense it's not your problem to find
fault in others in the same sense it's
not your problem to be affected by
others faults or people finding faulty
or people finally why does that upset me
keep a family Fault in me that's what
people do you cannot possibly control
them as the good I said the power of the
fools of ignorant minds is to complain
they complain if you speak fast they
complain if you speak too low too slow
some people will some people say I don't
like because he speaks too large some
people say I don't like that he speaks
too quiet not loud enough this is always
going to be something the people will
complain about why isn't my problem
other people's complaints and if you
already have that that doesn't mean I
don't care what other people say means I
don't make a problem out of it which
means I will not lose the context in
regards to what they are saying and then
you might oh yeah maybe I am speaking
too loud or too fast what's the purpose
of my speaking oh it's to convey the
message so which which is a better way to convey
so which which is a better way to convey
the message and fulfill the purpose but
purpose of my speaking oh maybe I should
speak slowly or oh it doesn't really
matter how I speak people can slow it
down okay then I want I won't deal with
it because it's not my problem but if
you are affected by other people's
complaints you will not have that
context in that perspective to review
your own behavior and see oh actually I
was simply careless about it it's not a
big deal to me but it's a big deal to
everybody else so what could change I
don't mind I'm not conceited I must hold
it that's again that's like in the
suitors when like a vast majority people
complain about something completely
insignificant there's nothing to do with
practice or anything and then the Buddha
said okay you stop doing it and you're
my why did you two get into this
complaint you should draw a line like
well you could draw a line but they'll
make people complain more with me now to
deal with that and if you deal with that
you won't be able to deal with your own
practice and seclusion and being left
alone so practically speaking if you
meet the requirement ignorant
requirement of the fools are complained
you'll be left alone and if you still
have work to do you want to be left
alone if you don't have a work to do if
you completed your work in terms of dumb
yeah deal with complaints talk back
whatever you want to do but if you still
recognize there's work to be done in you
have to be careful to protect the
environment they will support their work
so it's not like you don't care about
people complaining means I'll dismiss
everybody or I'll fight back it simply
means I won't lose perspective on what's
important to me that's it and by the way
that supplies too late because we're not
just monks I mean that's like one of the
main characteristics in the world well
with other people say about me and you
live your whole life governed by it and
I have people kind of try to dismiss
that and say I don't care what others
say and then go to the other extreme
well no you can try and deny caring what
I would say by the way you hear whatever
they say which means it affects you to
some extent so it's all about complying
blindly nor resisting blindly
it's about not being affected in the
first place and then it doesn't matter
whether you comply or you have a reason
for resisting like sometimes it would I
have reasons and resisted the vast
majority of people say Mao should be
doing he said no he wasn't always you go along
he said no he wasn't always you go along
with the majority it basically it's
determined by the context at a time when
all those when he was a group of those
monks were kind of living in dependence
of that whole area and then in this it
was mentioned the citizen they would
well basically they were like
householders in robes they would go and
spend time with lay people with their
homes talking about their lay affairs
laughing with him joking with him
associating with him so I'll come here
offer this of that like just the whole
like living basically like a kind of
full-on part of that lay Society and
then the monk was actually banned to
practicing the Dharma came to the
village and went in the pattern he
wasn't looking at people he wasn't
talking to them he wasn't smiling at
them and all these problems got upset
saying look at his conceited monk our
monks they talk to us they're friendly
with us they listen to our advice state
you know what we say so this shouldn't
take too long with it but this monk
doesn't mean look at us
the key is conceded he's this he's that
and they refused to give him the food
and he would think now if you were to
follow majority rule okay so in that
province we all must behave like this
well no well the Buddha Daly said to
Sally Potter collect a greater amount of
monks more than the monks they lived in
and go there and behave like that monk
there was quiet and when this vast
majority of monks came behaving quietly
not looking not smiling not chatting
with them then they realized oh crap
actually he was the monks the windows
were there the ones behaving differently
this is how the monk should behave so
the buddha corrected the lay people's
expectations and views which in a way
was nothing unreasonable something
unreasonable for you to say thank you
Frank give you food otherwise they don't
want to smile as hell thank you I really
appreciate it
why is it wrong but it's not who don't
even look at me cereal is even seemingly
reasonable stuff it's not reasonable if
it's rooted in unreasonable expectations
in views basically craving and greed in
a version pleases me this pleases me
and the Buddha first had great the
context whereby this type of behavior is
more conducive for the future
generations as well because yes those
monks might have been able to handle
associating with laypeople but those
monks they would be monks who will come
later on who will not be able to handle
it but we'll see that as the way of
doing things associating yeah let's get
together do festivals together spend
time together sit in the groups together
go for walks together but they will not
be able to handle it and then the dam
over the road is a result of it but if
you're able to handle it
then you're also able to not do it as
well so if those monks were able to
handle laypeople and surrounded by
laypeople which some of them were means
they're also then able to handle not
engaging with lay people with the
greatest perspective exactly by the way
they would be unaffected in other words
sometimes you circumstantially can be
involved with lay people it's it's the
motivation behind it gonna determine and
you will know where the motivation is
good or bad wholesome or unwholesome if
you review it and you see that what if
I'm not involved would I be affected or
emotionally and then you realize yes
means okay so I'm not impartial to this
I'm not indifferent to this if you truly
don't mind then it's fine like the
venerable China who is another hunt and
then when sorry Putin mock Mogollon I
went to see him and they questioned him
whether he's enough when he said he is
but he didn't believe in they went to
the bull up and said oh by the way he
died he committed he used the knife
because he was sick and so on what was
his destination they would have said
well he didn't he said he's an elephant
and they said well he did say he was in
that hunt but he was also associating
with bad families like there's no there
wasn't a good reputation going around
and the Buddha said well yes but one is
not blameworthy by associating with bad
families one is blameworthy by leaving
this body and taking up another as in
not being in other hand that's why you
blame body and then he tells sorry
Buddha McCollough what [\h__\h] who islands
themselves he said I reassure you
whenever China used that knife
blamelessly he died
pling he died Inara he was in Ireland
before he died
so you realize then okay so although
externally he was associating with his
bad families which would have not set a
good example for other monks will not be
able to handle it there was probably
some practical or circumstantial reason
that resulted in that he wasn't rooted
in his greed aversion delusion that made
him then forsake the context and engage
with bad families doesn't mean he was
doing bad stuff so the motivation the
intention behind the action determines
it you cannot judge it simply because oh
look the way he walks means he is that
the way he holds the cup means he's
ignorant oh he chooses to do this that
means he is such and such nope that's
you projecting your own meaning into it
into that if to that extent means you're
unaware of your own meaning behind it [Applause]